I remember back in the days of radio
that one of the popular programs on the
air which was later then made into a
television program was called Truth or
Consequences where the contestants would
be asked a question and if they failed
to give the proper response then they'd
have to go through some kind of silly
penalty
well as We Gather now for this course an
overview of the history of philosophy I
would like to think of this course in
terms of the idea of truth and
consequences
because sometimes it's important for us
to stop and think that ideas have
consequences in fact just about
everything that happens in this world
is preceded by some idea
an artist doesn't produce his work
without first having some concept in his
mind of what it is he wants to create in
his medium
but a far beyond the realm of Art and
music the whole concept of political
Theory by which nations rise and by
which they fall are all related in the
final analysis to ideas to Concepts and
so it's very important particularly for
Christians to understand something about
the historical process of theoretical
thought and how ideas have interacted
with our own Christian faith and belief
system
and so what I want to do is give a brief
historical overview this is of an
introductory nature this is not an
advanced course in technical
philosophy so we'll be skating lightly
over the surface of the historical
progress now obviously when we begin our
study of philosophy we're going to be
looking at it in terms of the history of
Western philosophical thought and the
textbooks will frequently tell us that
Western philosophy started on May the
28th
BC now I'm not exactly sure what time of
the day that was that that philosophy
was born
well the reason for this date is not
arbitrary
but it is because on this date in
antiquity
a solar eclipse took place
and what was so extraordinary about this
eclipse of the sun was that it was
predicted in advance by a very capable
scientist whose name was thales
and thales lived in Ionia
and he is generally regarded to be the
founder of ancient Greek philosophy now
this date's important to us for this
reason from a Christian perspective we
know that long before thales began his
inquiry into philosophical matters that
a lot of philosophical thinking had been
done in the East and certainly in the uh
among the Hebrews because we have a
philosophical depository of great
richness that is found in the Old
Testament that predates the work of
thales but here we're focusing on the
development of a special school of
thought a special science
that we associate with ancient Greek
civilization
so the first group of philosophers that
we will look at by way of introduction
is that group of philosophers called the
pre
socratics
that's a pretty simple concept isn't it
pre means beforehand and the
pre-socratics refer
to those philosophers who were engaged
in their work before Socrates now just
about everybody's heard about Socrates
and his famous student Plato and Plato's
famous student
Aristotle and so on but philosophy in
the west did not begin with Socrates
there was a significant development of
theoretical thought before Socrates ever
appeared on the scene and so when we
look at Origins we start with this fella
by the name of thales
now what thales was trying to solve
was perhaps the the most ancient
question of all that thinkers grappled
with and wrestled with and we can call
that the question or the problem of the
one and the many
the one and the many another way that we
can describe this problem or this
question is by speaking of the
relationship between unity and diversity
I frequently talk about the simple word
that we hear every day the word universe
or the word university
and the term universe is one of those
Mongrel words where we take two diverse
words and kind of jam them together and
coin an entirely new word and the two
words that are jammed together to create
the word Universe are the words unity
and diversity
and so the very idea of a universe
is that we are living in a system of
reality that has all kinds
of specific different things
there we Behold a multitude of diverse
objects we see chickens and pigs and
grass and flowers and houses and Roads
and cars all these specific individual
things that are diverse one from another
well the ancient Greek philosopher was
asking the question how do all these
bits of reality that we encounter every
day
fit together
is there anything that provides Unity
to this wide diversity of experience
that we have
is the world in which we live
a symphony in the final analysis or is
it cacophony
Carl Sagan raised the question is it
Cosmos or is it chaos and the difference
between Cosmos and chaos is simply the
difference
between an orderly structure
and that which admits to no order and
anything that is ordered has to have
something that makes everything cohere
that makes everything Unified
now we go away from the world universe
and we go to the word university
and that is an institution where
allegedly we go to look at the
individual disciplines like biology and
chemistry and astronomy and Mathematics
and sociology and history and psychology
and all these different disciplines
where you can go to one school and learn
all about these diverse fields of
inquiry but the assumption is that in
the University
we can discover
an integrated coherent view of the world
in which we live
now that whole question of the one and
the many
unity and diversity
was the question that this scientist in
the 6th Century BC by the name of thales
was passionately engaged in trying to
resolve
and what he was looking for is what we
call Ultimate
Ultimate Reality
now what does he mean or what do the
ancient thinkers mean by Ultimate
Reality
well
one of the technical terms that we learn
in the study of philosophy is the word
metaphysics
and we're all familiar with the term
physics
because physics describes the natural
world
of forces and powers and things and how
they interact
metaphysics is the attempt by the
philosopher to go above and beyond
the seeing world that we encounter with
our five senses from day to day
to search for that which is above and
beyond the Physical Realm from which
everything comes and by which everything
gains its ultimate unity and harmony
another concern that the ancient Greeks
had
was for the word that they called Telos
we get the word teleology from this word
Talos
and the Greek word tell us can be
translated by the English words end
or goal
or purpose
and so the question of sayles and of the
ancient philosophers was not simply what
is everything made of and how did it
come to pass
but also the deeper question of why
why are things the way that they are is
there any purpose for Birds is there a
purpose for wind and for water for stars
and for for the moon and is there any
purpose to human existence that was a
serious
theological teleological question that
is they're asking for the goal or the
end this is a profoundly theological
question for those of us who are
Christians in fact the old Westminster
shorty catechism begins with the first
question what is man's Chief end that is
it's asking what is the purpose or the
tell-offs of human existence well these
were the kinds of questions that were
being raised by the pre-socratic
philosophers
I once talked to a fella who's currently
the head of the philosophy Department of
a very prestigious University in America
and I knew him when he was a student
and he was working on his PhD in
philosophy at that time and we were
having a conversation
and he said you know
the thing that amazes me most about
philosophy and I said no what's that and
he said
all of the questions
that have wrestled with by modern
thinkers
were already explored in antiquity
and he said I've discovered there are
only so many questions to ask about
reality and those fellows back there
asked them all maybe they weren't quite
as refined and sophisticated as some
later thinkers were but at a fundamental
introductory way the ancient
pre-socratic philosophers were honing in
on the most basic questions of human
existence well again the first question
is
what is
this Ultimate Reality or for the Greek
it was the question what is The RK the
chief the ruling
stuff out of which everything comes
it was the search
for essence
when we talk about the word essence we
talk about essence or substance
or the simplest word is stuff
I remember when I lived in Holland was
going to school over there and trying to
learn that language and and was
impressed by how graphic the language
was because we went to the store to get
a vacuum sweeper and we discovered that
the name of a vacuum sweeper was a stuff
sucker which literally means a stuff
sucker you run this machine over the
carpet and it sucks up all of the stuff
that is there so we can get somewhat
abstract when we talk about essence or
substance or we can get right down to
the nitty-gritty when we're talking
about the stuff of life and of reality
well for thales
thaley said that the ultimate Essence
the ultimate stuff the ultimate
substance The RK
the Ultimate Reality from which
everything comes
in the universe
is water
now do you remember when Paul met with
the philosophers on Mars Hill in Athens
at the seat of ancient culture and he
engaged in some discussions with these
philosophers on that occasion it was the
stoics and the epicureans
and he noticed that they had an altar to
an unknown God and he then began to
preach to them and he said that which
you Worship in ignorance I declare to
you in power and didn't even your poets
understand that it is within God or in
him that we live
and move and have our being
remember that
three things that Paul said about God
that in God we live
we move
we have our being
now Paul understood I'm sure at that
time that he was addressing the three
biggest questions of ancient philosophy
because the ancient philosopher and
scientists like thales was interested in
what is the being or substance or stuff
out of which everything comes
what is the stuff or substance or origin
of life
and
how can we account
for this great mystery of motion
why do things move how did they get
started moving in the first place you
hear cosmetology cosmologist telling us
today about their theories of the origin
of the universe the Big Bang idea where
for all eternity all of the matter and
energy of the universe was compressed
into this infinitesimal point of
Singularity remained organized and
stable
presumably for eternity and then on one
Wednesday afternoon a two o'clock boom
it blows up and the question is begged
immediately is if there is such a laws
as the law of inertia the things that
are at rest stay at rest unless acted
upon by an outward outside force you ask
what was the outside force that stepped
into this picture of
Eternal organization and caused this
explosive change
in other words
who moved
something moved
how did that motion start
those are the questions that theylease
was was trying to answer and again we
might smile or even smirk when we hear
that his answer to all of these things
was water
seemed so naive and pre-scientific and
unsophisticated to us but think about it
for a moment first of all in trying to
understand
uh being
the essence of things
he noticed that everything in his
experience
whether they were animals vegetables or
minerals
appeared to his eyes
in one of three forms
his whole experience of reality was an
experience of things that were either
solid
or liquid
or gas
and he said no matter how diverse this
diversity is we can reduce everything
that we encounter to one of these three
things a solid a liquid or gas now he
said if I can look beyond that and say
is there some underlying metaphysical
stuff that will account for these three
different forms of things
and so he looked for a substance
that had the power or the ability to
exist in any of these three forms and
what was the most obvious candidate it
was water
in its natural state is a liquid when it
freezes it becomes a solid and when it
evaporates it becomes steam or a gas
and so he said so everything must be
made out of water
either in the hardened form like ice or
the liquid form or the gaseous form
and they said okay
how can I account for life
well all of the life that I discover
around me seems to require water
for a seed to grow it must
become wet before it can germinate
and for human beings and animals and
flowers and grass to grow and to
continue to live requires a constant
replenishing with water
seems to be necessary
to life
and if that's the case
then maybe it is the most basic
substance
that creates life itself
so now he has a preliminary answer to
the problem of being
the problem of life
but he still was left with the problem
of
motion how can I account for motion
he said well to account for motion
in light of a primitive understanding of
inertia he said
we have to look for some substance that
is high low
zoeistic
now that's just a fancy word
that means self-propelled
something that has the ability to move
itself we have a word for that in
English and it's the word
Otto which means self right
mobile
an automobile is something that has the
power of mobility in and of itself at
least when it's working and the gas tank
is filled and so on then you don't have
to push it to make it go but the idea of
of motion being explained required that
something somehow somewhere had the
ability to move itself because if
everything were at rest
and eternally at rest
and if the law of inertia is true
how long would it stay at rest
forever
and when we see something move like this
chalk up in the air
we realize that the chalk is is is still
now it's inert until acted upon by an
outside force which is my hand and I
exert pressure my arm is moving I let go
of the chalk and the chalk moves
so motion is caused by some previous
motion
and if that previous motion is caused by
motion prior to that
then we have to ask what caused that
motion
and we keep asking that question how
long
forever and we get into an infinite
regress that doesn't make any sense
unless we find something that has the
ability
to move
on its own
well for thales
that was water
because water has the ability to move
how did he know that by observing Rivers
and he noticed that Creeks were running
that there was a tie there was a current
of moving water he noticed that he
couldn't see anything that was tugging
at the Seas to make them move he didn't
know anything about the tidal forces of
the gravitational pull of the moon and
that sort of thing to his naked eye in
Antiquity it seemed like water was
churning and moving on its own
without being dependent on something
outside of itself
so you look at these things and you say
wow maybe he wasn't so foolish after all
because he's given us a basic
explanation
for being
for life
and for motion
and so for him
the answer to all of the Mysteries of
the one and the many
could be found in one Ultimate Reality
called water